ABHINAV VERMA

http://averma.tech/

Computer Science \circ University of Texas at Austin

(217) 721-9461 \circ verma@utexas.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research lies at the intersection of machine learning and formal methods. I am especially concerned with building trustworthy intelligent systems, using learning models that are provably safe, human interpretable, reliable, and robust to domain shifts.

EDUCATION

University of Texas at Austin

Ph.D. student o Computer Science

Advisor: Prof. Swarat Chaudhuri

Pin H. in the Computer Science Austin, TX

Rice University (Transferred to UT)August 2016 - August 2020Ph.D. student \circ Computer ScienceHouston, TX

University of Oregon

M.S. ○ Mathematics

September 2012 - June 2014

Eugene, OR

Indian Institute of Science

M.S. • Mathematics

August 2008 - July 2011

Bangalore, India

Thesis: Irreducible Representations of the Symmetric Group and the General Linear Group

University of Delhi - Hindu College
B.A. Honors o Mathematics

July 2005 - June 2008

New Delhi, India

PUBLICATIONS

Google Scholar Profile: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jM1HeCIAAAAJ

Peer-Reviewed

1. Programmatically Interpretable Reinforcement Learning

<u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Vijayaraghavan Murali, Rishabh Singh, Pushmeet Kohli, Swarat Chaudhuri 35th International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**) 2018.

Acceptance Rate: 29.1%

Accepted as a Long Talk: Top 9% of submitted papers.

2. Representing Formal Languages: A Comparison of Finite Automata and Recurrent Neural Networks

Joshua J. Michalenko, Ameesh Shah, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Swarat Chaudhuri, Ankit B. Patel 7th International Conference on Learning Representations (**ICLR**) 2019. Acceptance Rate: 31.4%

3. Control Regularization for Reduced Variance Reinforcement Learning Richard Cheng, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Gábor Orosz, Swarat Chaudhuri, Yisong Yue, Joel W. Burdick 36th International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**) 2019. Acceptance Rate: 22.6%

4. Imitation-Projected Programmatic Reinforcement Learning
<u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Hoang M. Le, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri
33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (**NeurIPS**) 2019.
Acceptance Rate: 21.6%

5. Learning Differentiable Programs with Admissible Neural Heuristics Ameesh Shah, Eric Zhan, Jennifer J Sun, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%

6. Neurosymbolic Reinforcement Learning with Formally Verified Exploration Greg Anderson, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Isil Dillig, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (**NeurIPS**) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%

Technical Report

Verifiable and Interpretable Reinforcement Learning through Program Synthesis
 <u>Abhinav Verma</u>
 Doctoral Consortium at The 33rd AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) 2019.

AWARDS & HONORS

- Fellowship, J.P. Morgan AI Research PhD Fellowship 2020. \$100,000 award to support tuition, stipend, and travel.
- Research Award, Dean Award, School of Engineering, Rice University 2019.
- Bronze, ACM Student Research Competition at Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) 2018.
- Bronze, ACM Student Research Competition at The 45th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL) 2018.
- Fellowship, Council of Scientific & Industrial Research (NSF-Equivalent), India 2011.
- Scholarship, Ministry of Human Resource Development, India 2008-2010.

MENTORING

Six students co-advised, three from underrepresented groups, two associated publications.

Current

• Masters, Surya S Dwivedi, University of Texas at Austin.

Project: Reinforcement learning for F1Tenth cars.

• Undergraduate, Myra Cheng, Caltech.

Project: Machine learning for behavioral neuroscience.

• Undergraduate, Joshua Deng, University of Texas at Austin.

Project: Learning programmatic models of RNA splicing.

Graduated

• Masters, Ameesh Shah, Rice University.

Project: Learning differentiable programs with admissible neural heuristics.

Currently: Graduate Student at UC Berkeley.

Abhinav Verma - CV 2 of 4

• Undergraduate, Jacqui Lee, Rice University.

Project: Adaptive therapies for Sepsis via reinforcement learning.

Currently: Graduate Student at MIT.

• Intern, Nirha Patel, University of California, San Diego.

Project: Evolutionary algorithms for reinforcement learning.

Currently: Developer at Yahoo.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Rice University

January 2017 - December 2019

Teaching Assistant

- COMP 539: Software Engineering Methodology.

 Project based graduate course on software engineering.
- COMP 503: Reasoning About Software.

 Graduate course on formal methods and automated reasoning.
- COMP 310: Advanced Object-Oriented Programming and Design. Senior undergraduate course on OOP.

Wolfram Research

January 2015 - August 2016

Certified Instructor

- Conducted online corporate training for Mathematica users.
- Helped develop and improve courses based on newly introduced functionality.

University of Oregon

September 2012 - June 2014

Standalone Instructor

Approximately forty students in each class.

- Math 105: University Mathematics.
 - Introduction to logic, combinatorics, and probability.
 - Core requirement for BS degree.
- Math 111: College Algebra.
 - Foundational course in algebra, functions, and mathematical modeling.
 - Calculus preparation course, prerequisite for higher-level math courses.
- Math 112: Elementary Functions.
 - Focus on mathematical induction and trigonometric functions.
 - Precalculus designed for math, biology, physiology, and CS majors.

Teaching Assistant

• Math 243: Introduction to Probability and Statistics. Undergraduate course on statistical reasoning.

Dr. B. R. Ambedkar University

January 2012 - April 2012

Teaching Assistant

• M01: Introduction to Mathematical Thinking. First course on abstract mathematics.

Abhinav Verma - CV 3 of 4

RESEARCH POSITIONS

SRI International

June 2019 - August 2019

Research Intern, Mentor: Susmit Jha

Menlo Park, CA

- Researched interpretable reinforcement learning via program synthesis.
- Integrated vision models with programmatic reinforcement learning.

Microsoft Research

June 2017 - September 2017

Research Intern, Mentor: Christoph M. Wintersteiger

Cambridge, UK

- Researched methods to use deep neural networks for quantifier instantiation in Z3.
- Intern in the Programming Principles and Tools group.

Wolfram Research

August 2014 - August 2016

Champaign, IL

Technology Engineer

- Researched integrating automated theorem proving into the Wolfram Language.
- Helped identify and implement new functionality based on cutting edge research.

SERVICE

Referee

- The 9th International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2021.
- Machine Learning (Springer Journal).
- The 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020.
- The 23rd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2020.
- The 32nd International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV) 2020.
- The 12th NASA Formal Methods Symposium (NFM) 2020.

INVITED PARTICIPATION

- Neurosymbolic Learning Seminar, University of Pennsylvania 2020.
- The New York Academy of Sciences, 14th Annual Machine Learning Symposium 2020.
- International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV), New York 2019.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Long Beach 2019.
- International Conference on Learning Representations, New Orleans 2019.
- International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, Vancouver 2019.
- Doctoroal Consortium at AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Honolulu 2019.
- Deep Learning and Reinforcement Learning Summer School, University of Alberta 2019.
- Marktoberdorf Summer School on Engineering Secure and Dependable Software Systems 2018.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Stockholm, Sweden 2018.
- Wolfram Technology Conference, Champaign, Illinois 2014.
- Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, University of Colorado, Boulder 2014.
- Graduate Student Topology and Geometry Conference, University of Texas, Austin 2014.
- Pacific Northwest Geometry Seminar, Stanford University 2014.
- Midwest Dynamical Systems Meeting, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2013.
- Workshop on Unitary Representations of Real Reductive Groups, University of Utah 2013.

Abhinav Verma - CV 4 of 4